J. L. M. Curry Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
J. L. M. Curry Papers 1637-1939 1866-1903
MSS17418
Curry, J. L. M. (Jabez Lamar Monroe), 1825-1903
3,900 items
30 containers
6.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Statesman, author, clergyman, diplomat, and educator. Diaries, correspondence, printed matter, clippings, memorabilia, notes and memoranda, legal papers, accounts, lectures and sermons, essays, scrapbook, manuscript of autobiography, speeches, and articles, and catalog of Curry's library. Includes autographs of presidents, Confederate leaders, Spanish noblemen, royalty, and writers, jurists, diplomats, educators, historians, scientists, reformers, artists, statesmen, literary figures, clergymen, and military men of the United States and Europe.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848--Autographs.; Aiken, William, 1806-1887--Correspondence.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916--Correspondence.; Bayard, Thomas F. (Thomas Francis), 1828-1898--Correspondence.; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852--Autographs.; Courtenay, William Ashmead, 1831-1908--Correspondence.; Curry, J. L. M. (Jabez Lamar Monroe), 1825-1903.; Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901--Correspondence.; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893--Correspondence.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790--Autographs.; Fuller, Melville Weston, 1833-1910--Correspondence.; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849--Autographs.; Gilman, Moses Coit--Correspondence.; Green, Samuel A. (Samuel Abbott), 1830-1918--Correspondence.; Hayes, Rutherford B., 1822-1893--Correspondence.; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859--Autographs.; Jackson, Henry R. (Henry Rootes), 1820-1898--Correspondence.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826--Autographs.; Johnson, Andrew, 1808-1875--Autographs.; Lyman, Theodore, 1833-1897--Correspondence.; Madison, James, 1751-1836--Autographs.; Onís, Luis de, 1762-1827--Autographs.; Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849--Autographs.; Porter, James D. (James Davis), 1828-1912--Correspondence.; Rush, Richard, 1780-1859--Autographs.; Stearns, Eben S. (Eben Sperry), 1819-1887--Correspondence.; Stuart, Alexander H. H. (Alexander Hugh Holmes), 1807-1891--Correspondence.; Waddel, Moses, 1770-1840--Correspondence.; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852--Autographs.; Wellington, Arthur Wellesley, Duke of, 1769-1852--Autographs.; Williams, Roger, 1604?-1683--Autographs.; Winthrop, Robert C. (Robert Charles), 1809-1894--Correspondence.
Organizations
John F. Slater Fund for the Education of Freedmen.; Peabody Education Fund.; Southern Education Board.
Subjects
African Americans--Education.; Artists--Autographs.; Authors, Spanish--Autographs.; Autographs--Collections.; Baptists--Southern States.; Clergy--Autographs.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Spain.; Diplomats--Autographs.; Diplomats--Confederate States of America--Autographs.; Education--Southern States.; Educators--Autographs.; Historians--Autographs.; Lawyers--Autographs.; Nobility--Spain--Autographs.; Presidents--United States--Autographs.; Reformers--Autographs.; Scientists--Autographs.; Soldiers--Autographs.; Statesmen--Autographs.
Places
Confederate States of America--Politics and government.; Spain--Foreign relations--United States.; Spain--Kings and rulers--Autographs.; United States--Foreign relations--Spain.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Occupations
Authors.; Clergy.; Diplomats.; Educators.; Statesmen.
Acquisition Information
The papers of J. L. M. Curry, statesman, author, clergyman, diplomat, and educator, were given to the Library of Congress by his sister, Mrs. J. K. Connally, in 1911, and by his nieces in 1940. Additional material was purchased.
Additional Guides
A brief description of Part I of the collection appears in the Library of Congress Handbook of Manuscripts (1918): 95, 306. A list of autographs in the collection is available as a PDF document.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include microfilm of originals in the Alabama Department of Archives and History, Montgomery, Ala.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of J. L. M. Curry are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1825, June 5 Born, Lincoln County, Georgia
1843 Graduated, University of Georgia, Athens, Ga.
1846 Received law degree, Dane Law School, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1857 1861 Member of Congress, resigned at outbreak of Civil War
1861 1965 Member, Confederate congresses; served in Confederate Cavalry
1865 1868 President, Howard College, Homewood, Ala.
1868 1881 Professor, Richmond College, Richmond, Va. (president of trustees, 1882-1886, 1890-1897)
1881 Became general agent of Peabody Education Fund
1885 1888 Declined cabinet post to become minister to Spain
1890 Became agent and director of John F. Slater Fund for the Education of Freedman
1899 Head, Southern Education Board
1902 Returned to Spain as ambassador extraordinary
1903, Feb. 12 Died, Asheville, N.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Jabez Lamar Munroe Curry (1825-1903) consist of diaries, correspondence, an autograph collection, printed matter, clippings, memorabilia, notes and memoranda, legal papers, accounts, lectures and sermons, essays, scrapbooks, a manuscript of an autobiography, speeches and articles, and miscellaneous material. The collection spans the years 1637-1939, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1866-1903. The papers are organized into two parts. Part I is composed of a Correspondence and General File. Part II consists of four series: Correspondence, Autographs, Diaries, and Miscellany.
Included in the Autographs series are correspondence and letters (many to Curry himself) from United States presidents; Confederate statesmen; Spanish noblemen, royalty, and writers; and American and European artists, clergyman, diplomats, educators, historians, jurists, literary figures, military men, reformers, scientists, and statesmen. Among the signatories are John Quincy Adams, Henry Clay, Benjamin Franklin, Albert Gallatin, Washington Irving, Thomas Jefferson, Andrew Johnson, James Madison, Luis de Onís, James K. Polk, Richard Rush, Daniel Webster, Arthur Wellesley, Duke of Wellington, and Roger Williams.
Reports, journals, writings, printed matter, and other material in the Miscellany series are organized mainly in bound volumes designated as Record Books A to G compiled by Curry. Subjects in the collection concern topics such as the Peabody Education Fund, the John F. Slater Fund for the Education of Freedmen, the Southern Education Board, Curry’s studies on Civil War history and the civil government of the Confederacy, and diplomatic matters in Spain.
The Diaries and much of the correspondence relate to Curry’s career as an educator, diplomat, and Baptist minister. Correspondents include William Aiken, James Burrill Angel, Thomas F. Bayard, William Ashmead Courtenay, William Maxwell Evarts, Hamilton Fish (1808-1893), Melville Weston Fuller, Moses Coit Gilman, Rutherford Birchard Hayes, Samuel A. Green, Henry R Jackson, Theodore Lyman, James D. Porter, Eben S. Stearns, Alexander H. H. Stuart, Moses Waddel, and Robert C. Winthrop.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series in two parts:
Part I:
Correspondence and General File, 1809-1903
Part II:
Correspondence, 1824-1939
Autographs, 1637-1895
Diaries, 1866-1902
Miscellany, 1886-1902
Container List
- Part I: Correspondence and General File, 1809-1903 (Box I:1-I:18)
  Bound volumes of letters received by Curry and his wife. Includes reports, writings, and printed matter.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1809-1876 (Box I:1)
  - 1877, May 5-1881, Aug. 18 (Box I:2)
  - 1881, Aug. 19-1882, Nov. 12 (Box I:3)
  - 1882, Nov. 13-1884, Dec. 25 (Box I:4)
  - 1884, Dec. 26-1886, Oct. 30 (Box I:5)
  - 1886, Nov. 9-1888, Nov. 8 (Box I:6)
  - 1888, Nov. 9-1890, Feb. 11 (Box I:7)
  - 1890, Feb. 12-1891, May 12 (Box I:8)
  - 1891, May 13-1892, Apr. 11 (Box I:9)
  - 1892, Apr. 12-1893, Dec. 27 (Box I:10)
  - 1893, Dec. 28-1896, Jan. 29 (Box I:11)
  - 1896, Jan. 30-1899, Oct. 30 (Box I:12)
  - 1899, Oct. 31-1901, Dec. 30 (Box I:13)
  - 1901, Dec. 31-1903, Feb. 9 (Box I:14)
  - 1903, Feb. 10-1908, June 8 (Box I:15)
  - Undated (Box I:16-18)
- Part II: Correspondence, 1824-1939 (Box II:1-II:6)
  Bound volumes of letters received by Curry and by others after his death.
  - 1824, July 14-1875, Feb. 27 (Box II:1)
  - 1875, Mar. 7-1878, July 1 (Box II:2)
  - 1878, Aug. 3-1888, Apr. 2 (Box II:3)
  - 1888, May 2-1892, Nov. 4 (Box II:4)
  - 1892, Nov. 7-1907, Nov. 4 (Box II:5)
  - 1901, Sept. 30-1939, Dec. 3 (Box II:6)
- Part II: Autographs, 1637-1895 (Box II:7)
  Letters of prominent Americans and Europeans, many to Curry, but also predating him, compiled as an autograph collection.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - A-Z, 1637-1895, (4 folders) (Box II:7)
- Part II: Diaries, 1866-1902 (Box II:7-II:9)
  Pocket diaries.
  - 1866-1876, (3 folders) (Box II:7)
  - 1880-1894, (4 folders) (Box II:8)
  - 1895-1902, (3 folders) (Box II:9)
- Part II: Miscellany, 1886-1902 (Box II:10-II:12)
  - Record Books A-C, (3 folders) (Box II:10)
  - Record Books D-G, (3 folders) (Box II:11)
  - Printed matter (Box II:12)
  - Congressional Directory, 1902 (Box II:12)